# 呲勺
"Zi"(mimetic word for the sound when fry things with oil) the spoon
# 三叔 多地道啊这个
Isn't it authentic, Sanshu
# 红绿相间 真漂亮
Colourful, Beautiful!
# 这灰了吧唧什么玩意
What's this grey-ish thing?
# 麻豆腐
Ma tofu
# 有很多人来北京说吃不惯麻豆腐
There are people that didn't like Ma tofu
# 吃不惯 他慢慢的越吃越香
and they gradually got used to it
# 咱们就做羊油的
we'll make one with mutton fat oil
# 人家吃不习惯怎么办
what if they didn't like it?
# 吃不习惯 素油炒这种技法也可以
Then we can do it with vege-oil instead
# 毛豆仁儿提前入一下味儿
We give some seasoning to the peeled soybean
# 大料 花椒粒 盐 别的不用加
Nothing but aniseed, Sichuan pepper, salt
# 这么简单 对
That easy? Yeah
# 好 十五分钟就行了
Alright, 15 mins should be enough
# 为了节省时间
To save some time
# 咱就先把雪里蕻焯一下水 因为它咸
We first boil the potherb mustard so that it's less salty
# 麻豆腐雪里蕻跟豆儿是绝配 离不开
Ma tofu and potherb mustard are the perfect match, you do not tear them apart
# 雪里蕻不能太少了
don't put too little potherb mustard
# 咱就干焙 不放油
we "ganbei"(fry with no oil)
# 其实雪里蕻是麻豆的筋骨
potherb mustard is the backbone of Ma tofu
# 专业术语叫魂儿 筋骨
technically speaking, the soul of Ma tofu
# 煮好的豆 最好是泡个一个小时
Boiled beans, it is the best to soak them in the seasoned water for an hour
# 大料 花椒那个味儿入进去
to ensure the beans have the flavour of aniseed and pepper
# 五香豆儿说白了就是
They are Wuxiang(Five flavours) beans, actually
# 熟了没有 不能糊弄我们网友
Is it cooked? Don't fool our audiance
# 正好
It's just right.
# 收收水气行了
dried potherb mustard out of the wok
# 咱们现在开始耗油
We now start to Haoyou(Season melted solid animal fat)
# 关键是在耗油
This is the crucial part
# 这个药料咱也先给它洗一下
Wash these Chinese Medicine(Traditional Chinese Medicine is also used for food seasoning)
# 有小茴香 豆蔻 香叶 辣椒 八角
fennel, cardamun, myrcia, aniseed
# 要葱油么 葱油更好
Do you need some Congyou(Oil seasoned with spring onion)?  That's even better
# 我给你炸好的
I made it for you
# 好 谢谢三叔
Thank you Sanshu
# 少放点 把我的全放里了
Ok,=-= you used it all
# 羊油 羊尾巴油
Mutton Fat, from the tail
# 再搁点葱出点葱香味
Give some fresh spring onions
# 把所有的料下下去
Now put all the Chinese Medicine in the wok
# 麻豆腐关键的是油 香香的
It's all about the oil, aromatic!
# 耗油的同时咱把口儿给它调出来
In the meantime we should start on the tofu
# 把雪里蕻加进去 豆儿
shove in the potherb mustard and beans
# 麻豆腐是什么做的
what is the tofu made of
# 绿豆 先得泡 泡完以后打碎了
Mung, you have to soak it in water for about a day and crush using blender
# 糗出来的
you must "qiu"(put all the crushed mung in a container for a while and it becomes slimy) this tofu
# 它那个汁儿提出来
the liquid we obtained after that can be fermentated
# 发酵完了就是豆汁
and it becomes DouZhi(another Beijing traditional food)
# 渣子就是麻豆腐
the remaining is the Ma tofu
# 这个东西离不开黄酱 澥好的黄酱
Diluted Soybean sauce is a must for this dish
# 香啊是吧 层次感很强
Aromatic right? Strong layed scent
# 稍微提一点糖 糖提鲜 来一点
Give it a little sugar for it to be Xian(The fifth flavour that human can taste)
# 酱油 胡椒粉
Soy sauce, pepper powder
# 还有秘诀 咱把炸好的葱捞出来
Secret in my recipe, get all the fried spring onions out
# 再切点葱末 没少用葱啊
chop more spring onions, we used a lot of onions
# 突出葱香味儿
to make the onion flavour stand out
# 看见没有网友 把炸好的葱切成末
Pay attention my friends, chop the fried onion into little chips
# 然后拌在里头吃着香
and mix it with the dish
# 下一个节目 豆汁
for our next trick, DouZhi!
# 用豆汁澥麻豆腐 原汁原味
we used Douzhi to dilute the Ma tofu as they are made of the same thing
# 香 酸香
Aromatic, It smells sour but aromatic(the smell of Douzhi)
# 咱们起锅坐油 关键是油
now we put a wok on the stove and pour in the oil
# 油可以多一点没关系 不要怕油大
we can use a little more oil, don't be afraid of using too much
# 既然做咱们就往传统上做
We will do it according to the tradition if we are to do this
# 想吃油少油多的自己去调整
You can adjust the amount of oil based on your own situation
# 再一次的大量的葱花 葱香味
LOTS OF ONION CHIPS!! The scent of onion
# 差不都了这菜
we are almost there
# 二十年专注京味菜
I've focused on Beijing cuisine for twenty years
# 讲究 香 离不开这香味
The scent of the dish had always played a big part in Beijing cuisine
# 有回味啊 改小火
There will be an after taste, turn down the gas
# 把麻豆腐下进去
shove the tofu in
# 跟炸酱面似的 待会弄碗面条得了
looks just like Zhajiang noodle's sauce, maybe make some noodles later
# 小火去推 必须得推
push it over a low flame
# 待会您看 这时候有油
You can see some oil floating
# 待会就没油了 全推进去了
and it will all be pushed into tofu a while later
# 小火慢慢熬 就跟炸酱似的
use a low flame just as you are making Zhajiang noodle's sauce
# 熬多长时间师父 一般
How long do we decoct it, master?
# 最少得二十分钟
20 mins at least
# 要如果有时间的话 四十分钟小火
40 mins over a low flame if you got time
# 慢慢儿推 炖透了
push it slowly
# 多香 糗透了
The smell is so good, :3 we've almost done the "Qiuing"
# 麻豆腐 酱 雪里蕻的香气
Ma tofu, soybean paste, the scent of potherb mustard
# 融合到一起 多棒
all mixed together beautifully! Awesome!
# 您看没油了是吧三叔
See how there is no more oil seen now, Sanshu?
# 咱们现在基本上推了二十分钟了
We've pushed it for 20 mins now
# 待会往外噗噗冒气 气顶勺
There will me more steam over time
# 像我这样推四十分钟（更香了）
Push it for 40 mins will make it more aromatic
# 来欢子推会儿 徒弟推
Come, Huanzi. Take my position for a while, apprentice should do the job
# 我推这还真是有经验
I am really experience in this
# 从小一来北京学徒就开始推这个
I have been doing this(pushing Ma tofu) since I was an apprentice when I first arrived Beijing
# 为什么他长得帅呢
Why is he good looking?
# 就因为推麻豆腐推的
Because he push a lot of Ma tofu
# 还手工灌肠 外边都是自己买
and make homemade sausages, other restaurants buy them
# 我们都是自己做
but we make our own sausages
# 这麻豆腐不搁羊油不搁酱
if you don't make Ma tofu with mutton fat and soybean paste
# 出不来香味
there will not be enough scent
# 一般咱们家使的都是豆油是吧
Chinese famillies usually have soybean oil in their home
# 各种花生油 豆油都可以
varies kind of peanut oil or soybean oil is ok
# 就是素油 都可以
vege oil even
# 素油也是这种方式
It's the same way if you choose to use vege oil
# 还是那句话
Once again,
# 你喜欢吃哪口儿
You can use whatever
# 你用哪口儿油 都可以
oil you like
# 关键是制料油跟葱油的时候
the crucial part is when you make the ani-oil and onion-oil
# 得制好了 一通百通
Have to make that right, and once you know the method there will be no strict rules when you cook
# 这个基本形状可以了
This shape looks good enough
# 出丝了 出丝了啊
There are filaments
# 差不多得了 翻下勺
That's ok, you don't have to do it anymore
# 一看立住了
Look, it stands by itself
# 咱刨一个坑儿
we make a hole on top
# 你知道这刨坑儿还不能说
Don't talk about the hole!
# 待会他们就全看见了
They will see it later
# 韭菜越搁越多越香 韭菜不能少了
The more Chinese chives you put in the more aromatic it gets
# 辣椒油呢 辣椒油待会现呲
where's the chilli oil? We will "Zi" the chilli oil.
# 欢子看你的手艺了今天
It's all on you Huan
# 师父考考你
let's see what you got
# 这是什么油 色拉油
what's this oil? Salad Oil
# 还是把辣椒洗一下
Let's wash the chilli first
# 洗一下油温高点没事
This way the oil temperture can be higher when "Zi" the spoon without overcooking the chilli
# 没问题
No Problem
# 关键是这呲啦一下
Carefull, It's neck or nothing
# 呲勺
"Zi" the spoon
# 三叔 多地道啊这个
So authentic right, Sanshu?
# 出锅喽
Ready to serve!
# 红绿相间 真漂亮
Colorful and beautiful
# 感觉怎么样三叔
How does it taste, Sanshu?
# 我有一种自豪感
I am very proud
# 太好了
Very good!
# 天上有 人间能有几回绝 是吧
How many times can you taste this while you are alive?(Chinese Idiom)
# 绝对北京味儿 做的好
Absolute Beijing Cuisine, Good job
# 好 谢谢叔儿
Right, Thank you Shu!
# 太好吃了
So delicious!
# 青韭 辣椒 颜色 口味
Green Chives, Chilli, Colour, Taste
# 关键你最后那辣椒 你看见没有
The last step when you "Zi" that chilli
# 那呲啦这一下 必须得到位了
that had to be done right!
# 说糊没糊 说没糊马上要糊了
It's not overcooked, but almost there.
# 那种回味
The after taste of that
# 韭菜的香气 辣椒的香气
The aroma of chives and chilli